A Guide to the Records of Governor Mark R. Warner, Office of the Special Advisor to the Governor for Workforce Development, 2003-2005
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Records of Governor Mark R. Warner, Office of the Special Advisor to the Governor for Workforce Development, 2003-2005
The Library of Virginia
41944
5 cubic feet, (5 boxes)
Office of the Special Advisor to the Governor for Workforce Development
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Transferred by Governor Mark R. Warner's Office of the Special Advisor to the Governor for Workforce Development, 27 March 2005.
Biographical/Historical Information
These records contain files from the Office of the Special Advisor to the Governor for Workforce Development. This appointed position was created in early 2003, and the specific duties were clarified by Senate Bill 304 of the 2004 legislative session. The advisor is responsible for serving as the liaison for workforce training with state and local government, the Virginia Workforce Council (VWC), local work investment boards, as well as the general business community. The advisor is also responsible for reviewing fund allocation, helping the VWC implement policies for the Virginia Workforce System, monitoring federal workforce-related legislation, and reporting annually on the condition of statewide workforce training programs. Dr. Barbara Bolin, formerly employed by the state of Michigan in a similar capacity, was appointed by Governor Warner as his advisor in June 2003. Dr. Bolin resigned her position in May 2005, and Dolores Esser of the Virginia Employment Commission was appointed to fill the vacancy in November 2005.
Scope and Content
Comprised of subject files containing a variety of material including correspondence, memos, reports and other working papers that document the activities of Dr. Bolin and the staff of the Office of the Special Advisor to the Governor for Workforce Development.
Arrangement
Organized into the following series:
Series I. Speaking Engagements and Meetings, 2003-2005
Series II. Local Workforce Investment Boards, 2004
Series III. Dr. Barbara Bolin's Files, 2003-2004
Series IV. Miscellaneous Files, 2003-2005
Contents List
- Series I. Speaking Engagements and Meetings, 2003-2005., Extent: 90 folders. (Box 1-2)
  Contains material pertaining to various speaking engagements, meetings and conferences attended by Dr. Bolin or other members of her staff. Most of these events were dedicated to workforce development trends and programs. The files are arranged chronologically by the date of the engagement. Most files contain correspondence, agendas, and other working papers that document the particular event.
  - National Governors' Association, Sept. 29-Oct. 1, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Arlington/Alexandria Workforce Investment Board--Briefing on Workforce Development, Jan. 7, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Virginia Association of Local Human Services Officials, Jan. 8-9, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - SWOT Analysis Meeting, Jan. 15, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Old Dominion Assembly, Jan. 21, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Virginia Chamber of Commerce, Winter Board of Directors' Meeting, Jan. 21-22, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Virginia Career Education Foundation Task Force Meeting, Jan. 22, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - U.S. Deptartment of Labor, State/Federal Policy Forum, Feb. 19, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Virginia Workforce Council, Executive Committee Meeting, Feb. 23, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Perkins Professional Development Conference, Mar. 9-10, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Eastern Region Focus Group, Mar. 11, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - National Association of Workforce Boards, Mar. 14-17, 2003 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Danville Community College Career Fair, Mar. 24-25, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Strategic Planning Meetings, Mar. 25, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Workforce Investment Board Lunch, Mar. 26, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Workforce Investment Board Lunch, Mar. 26, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Virginia Community College System, New Horizons Conference, Apr. 15, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Virginia Workforce Council, Key Player Effectiveness Committee Meeting, Apr. 15, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Worldwide Interactive Network Users Conference, Apr. 19-21, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Workforce Investment Board, Executive Directors' Meeting, Apr. 21, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Memorandum of Understanding/One-Stop Career Center Meeting, Apr. 29, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Rappahannock Community College Administrative Professionals Conference, Apr. 23, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Virginia Workforce Council, Metrics and Incentives Committee Meeting, May 3, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Virginia Workforce Council, Local Excellence Committee Meeting, May 4, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Career Readiness Certificate Meeting, May 5, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - CVS Pharmacy/Workforce Development Partnership Kick-off, May 5, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Workforce Investment Board, Executive Directors' Meeting, May 6-7, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - WorkKeys National Conference, May 12-14, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - National Governors' Association, Workforce Policy Academy III, May 17-19, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - U.S. Department of Labor Meeting/Trip to Wytheville, VA, May 24-27, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Middle Peninsula-Northern Neck Workforce Development Summit, June 4, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Virginia Workforce Council Meeting, June 15, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Workforce Investment Board, Executive Directors' Meeting, June 23, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Northern Virginia Technology Council/Virginia Association for Adult and Continuing Education, June 24, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Virginia Competency Analysis Profile System Meeting, July 8, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Workforce Innovations Conference, July 17-21, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - WorkKeys Seminar, July 23, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Workforce Academy, July 26, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - North Carolina Community College System WorkKeys User Group Kick-off, Aug. 4, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Virginia Workforce Council, Executive Directors' Meeting/WorkKeys Meeting, Aug. 16-18, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Workforce Information Grant Meeting, Aug. 20, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - National Association of State Workforce Board Chairs Meeting, Aug. 21-24, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Virginia Workforce Council Executive Directors' Meeting, Sept. 8, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Education Meeting, Sept. 9, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Crater Regional Workforce Investment Board Meeting, Sept. 9, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Southern Governors' Association Annual Meeting, Sept. 12-14, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Public Sector Employment for People with Disabilities Meeting, Sept. 27, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Worldwide Interactive Network Alabama Meeting, Sept. 28-29, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Missouri Workforce Conference, Oct. 6-8, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 49)
  - Society for Human Resource Management Conference, Oct. 8, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 50)
  - Virginia Workforce Council, Key Player Effectiveness Committee Meeting, OCt. 12, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 51)
  - Governor's Working Summit on Advancing Manufacturing in Virginia, Oct. 13-14, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 52)
  - Virginia Workforce Council Meeting, Oct. 18, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 53)
  - Workforce Investment Board, Executive Directors' Meeting, Oct. 18, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 54)
  - Governor's Conference on Workforce and Career Development, Oct. 18-21, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 55)
  - Career Readiness Certificate Launch, Oct. 19, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 56)
  - Career Readiness Certificate Launch, Oct. 19, 2004 (Box 1, Folder 57)
  - National Center on Education and the Economy, Local Elected Officials Meeting, OCt. 26, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - National Association of Manufacturers Meeting, Oct. 27-28, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Blue Ridge Television Interview, Nov. 1, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Bay Consortium Workforce Investment Board Meeting/Northern Virginia Investment Board Meeting, Nov. 3-4, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - WorkKeys Information Session, Nov. 9, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Workforce Investment Board, Executive Directors' Meeting, Nov. 9-10, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - National Center on Education and the Economy, Local Elected Officials Meeting/Randolph Community College Workforce Development Conference, Nov. 16-17, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Virginia Workforce Council Meeting, Systems Performance Measures Session, Nov. 18-19, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - South Carolina Education and Workforce Taskforce, Nov. 21-22, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Orangeburg-Calhoun Technical College President's Roundtable Meeting, Dec. 2, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Career Readiness Certificate Taskforce Meeting, Dec. 6, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - National Governors' Association, Maritime Skills Training Taskforce Meeting, Dec. 7, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Workforce Investment Board, Executive Directors' Meeting, Dec. 8, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Virginia Community College System Workforce Development and Continuing Education Peer Conference, Dec. 8-10, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - CLEO Consortium Luncheon/Executive Committee Meeting, Dec. 14-16, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - WorkKeys Regional Meetings, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - WorkKeys Regional Meetings, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Virginia Workforce Council Meeting, Jan. 6, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Workforce Investment Board, Executive Directors' Meeting, Jan. 19, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Workforce Investment Board, Executive Directors' Meeting, Feb. 9, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Virginia Workforce Council, Local Excellence Committee Meeting/Workforce Investment Board, Executive Directors' Joint Meeting, Feb. 25, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Virginia Workforce Council Meeting, Mar. 23, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - WorkKeys Presentation, Blue Ridge Community College, North Carolina/Knoxville and Chatanooga Trips, Apr. 6-8, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - American Association of Community Colleges Conference, Apr. 9-12, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - "Defining a Qualified Workforce" Seminar, Apr. 12-13, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Piedmont Workforce Network Board Meeting, Apr. 14, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Innovate America, National Summit on Regional Innovation, Apr. 22, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Virginia Association for Adult Continuing Education Luncheon, Apr. 27, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Spring Workforce Conference, Apr. 2005 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Governor's Conference, Apr. 2005 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Alabama Career Readiness Certificate Task Force Presentation, May 3, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Literacy Fair of Virginia, May 19, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Workforce Development Professional Competencies Course, July 18-22, 2005 (Box 2, Folder 33)
- Series II. Local Workforce Investment Boards, 2004., Extent: 47 folders. (Box 2-3)
  Contains material submitted by the statewide network of workforce investment boards. Local workforce investment boards are responsible for establishing and operating Virginia Workforce Centers, and for providing a forum to assure that workforce training and employment initiatives meet the economic and business needs for each of the seventeen areas. Although each board is given a number, most of the boards have names they use in place of the area number. In late 2004 each board was responsible for submitting action, business, and strategic plans for their body. These plans document the budgets and activities of each board until 2007. While most boards submitted three separate plans, some only submitted one or two, and others combined one or more into a single report. Also included in the files is correspondence relating to the creation and submission of these reports. The files are arranged alphabetically by the name of the investment board, with two folders at the end that contain information regarding Exemplary Performance and Local Coordination Monetary Incentive Awards.
  - Alexandria/Arlington Workforce System, Action Plan, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Alexandria/Arlington Workforce System, Business Plan, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Alexandria/Arlington Workforce System, Strategic Plan, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Bay Consortium Workforce Investment Board, Action Plan, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Bay Consortium Workforce Investment Board, Business Plan, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Bay Consortium Workforce Investment Board, Strategic Plan, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Capital Area Workforce Investment Board, Action Plan, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Capital Area Workforce Investment Board, Business Plan, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Capital Area Workforce Investment Board, Strategic Plan, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Crater Regional Workforce Investment Board, Action Plan, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Crater Regional Workforce Investment Board, Strategic Plan, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Greater Peninsula Workforce Development Consortium, Action Plan, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Greater Peninsula Workforce Development Consortium, Business Plan, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Greater Peninsula Workforce Investment Board/Greater Peninsula Workforce Development Consortium, Strategic Plan, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Greater Peninsula Workforce Investment Board/Greater Peninsula Workforce Development Consortium, Strategic Plan, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Hampton Roads Workforce Investment Board, Action Plan, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Hampton Roads Workforce Investment Board, Strategic Plan, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - New River/Mount Rogers Workforce Investment Board, Action Plan, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - New River/Mount Rogers Workforce Investment Board, Business Plan, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - New River/Mount Rogers Workforce Investment Board, Business Plan, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - New River/Mount Rogers Workforce Investment Board, Business Plan, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - New River/Mount Rogers Workforce Investment Board, Business Plan, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - New River/Mount Rogers Workforce Investment Board, Business Plan, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - New River/Mount Rogers Workforce Investment Board, Strategic Plan, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - New River/Mount Rogers Workforce Investment Board, Strategic Plan, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - New River/Mount Rogers Workforce Investment Board, Strategic Plan, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Northern Shenandoah Valley Workforce Investment Board, Action Plan, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Northern Shenandoah Valley Workforce Investment Board, Business Plan, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Northern Shenandoah Valley Workforce Investment Board, Strategic Plan, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Northern Virginia Workforce Investment Board, Action Plan, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Northern Virginia Workforce Investment Board, Business Plan, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Northern Virginia Workforce Investment Board, Strategic Plan, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Region 2000 Regional Commission (Central Virginia), Action Plan, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Region 2000 Regional Commission (Central Virginia), Business Plan, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Richmond Workforce Investment Board/Richmond Career Advancement Center, Action and Business Plan, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Richmond Workforce Investment Board, Strategic Plan, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Shenandoah Valley Workforce Investment Board, Action Plan, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Shenandoah Valley Workforce Investment Board, Business Plan, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - South Central Region Workforce Investment Board, Business Plan, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Southwest Virginia Workforce Investment Board (Area 1), Business Plan, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Thomas Jefferson Planning District Commission (Area 6), Business Plan, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Western Virginia Workforce Development Board, Business Plan, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - West Piedmont Workforce Investment Board, Action Plan, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - West Piedmont Workforce Investment Board, Business Plan, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - West Piedmont Workforce Investment Board, Strategic Plan, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Exemplary Performance and Local Coordination Monetary Incentive Award, Hampton Roads Workforce Development Board, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Exemplary Performance and Local Coordination Monetary Incentive Award, Northern Virginia Workforce Investment Board, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 24)
- Series III. Dr. Barbara Bolin's Files, 2003-2004., Extent: 12 folders. (Box 3)
  Contains files created by Dr. Bolin for her personal use. The material varies widely, but of possible interest are the files dealing with legislation affecting workforce development programs. The files are arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Department of Labor, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Glenn, Rob, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Homelessness, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Legislation, 2003-2004 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Legislation, 2003-2004 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Maritime Strategy, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Urban Institute, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Utah Department of Workforce Services, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - Virginia Employment Commission Policies, 2003 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Virginia Workforce Council, 2003-2004 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Workforce Investment Act, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  - Working Summit on Virginia Forest Industries, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 36)
- Series IV. Miscellaneous Files, 2003-2005., Extent: 58 folders. (Box 3-5)
  Contains various subject files. A wide range of subjects are addressed, such as the Career Readiness Certificate program, an assessment-based credential that gives employers and career seekers a uniform measure of key workplace skills, and was a focal point during Dr. Bolin's tenure. Also of interest are the folders devoted to the Maritime taskforce, and those that deal with statewide workforce strategic planning. The files are arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - "Career Kaleidoscope" Newsletter Submissions, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  - Career Readiness Certificate Consortium Meeting Invitations, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  - Career Readiness Certificate Consortium Meeting Invitations, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  - Career Readiness Certificate Consortium Meeting Invitations, 2005 (Box 3, Folder 40)
  - Career Readiness Certificate Information, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 41)
  - Career Readiness Certificates (blank), no date (Box 3, Folder 42)
  - Coordinated Economic Relief Centers, 2004 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  - Correspondence for Dr. Bolin, 2004-2005 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence for Dr. Bolin, 2004-2005 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Demand Planning, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Demand Planning and Certification, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - G Stars Software, no date (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - House Bill 526, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - House Bill 546, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - House Bill 1231 2004 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Integrated Performance Information for Workforce Development Report, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Legislation, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Maritime Taskforce, 2003-2004 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Maritime Taskforce, 2003-2004 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Marketing the Career Readiness Certificate, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Michigan Workforce Information, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Nursing Taskforce Survey and Information, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Office Stuff, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Olmstead Implementation Team, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - One-Stop Career Centers, 2005 (Box 4, Folder 18)
  - Performance Breakthroughs Inc., 2004-2005 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  - Personnel, 2003-2005 (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Purchases, 2004-2005 (Box 4, Folder 21)
  - Regional Competitiveness Act, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  - Resource Inventory Material, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 23)
  - Resource Inventory Material, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  - Review of Workforce Training in Virginia (Joint Legislative Audit and Review Commission), 2003 (Box 4, Folder 25)
  - Review of Workforce Training in Virginia (Joint Legislative Audit and Review Commission), 2003 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  - Richmond Workforce Investment Board Career Center Model Implementation, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  - Senate Bill 304, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  - Senate Bill 460, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 29)
  - Strategic Planning, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 30)
  - Strategic Planning Guidance, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Strategic Planning Meeting Material, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Strategic Planning Meeting Material, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - Strategic Planning Review, 2004 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Tidewater Community College Deptartment of Labor Ship Repair Training Initiative, Final Report, 2004 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Travel and Reimbursement Policies, 2003 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Trio Program (John O'Leary), 2005 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Virginia Community College System Workforce Development Project, 2004 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Virginia Electronic Commerce Technology Center, 2004 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Virginia Employment Commission, 2003-2004 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Virginia Workforce Council Annual Report, 2004 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Virginia Workforce Council/Workforce Investment Act, 2004 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Workforce Information Grant, 2004 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Workforce Information Grant, 2004 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Workforce Investment Act, Yearly Summary of Virginia, 2004 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Workforce Investment Board 3 Pilot, (no director), 2004-2005 (Box 5, Folder 12)
  - Workforce Investment Board 10, Coordinated Economic Relief Center Model, 2004 (Box 5, Folder 13)
  - Workforce Investment Board Planning and One-Stop Certification, 2004 (Box 5, Folder 14)
  - WorkKeys Booklet, no date (Box 5, Folder 15)
  - WorkKeys Profiles, 2004 (Box 5, Folder 16)
  - Work Readiness Credential, 2003 (Box 5, Folder 17)